The second phase of globalization covers the period of intensive
Giai đoạn thứ hai của toàn cầu hóa bao gồm thời kì quốc tế hóa sâu rộng
internationalization of transportation systems, communications, commerce,
về hệ thống giao thông, viễn thông, thương mại,
science, and many other human activities that unfolded between the
khoa học và nhiều ngành khác
middle of the 19th century and the collapse of second phase globalization
xuất hiện từ giữa thế kỷ 19 và sự sụp đổ của giai đoạn này
that resulted from the outbreak of war in August of 1914.
dẫn đến sự bủng nổ của Thế chiến 1 vào tháng 8/1914.
During the second half of the 19th century, the Western world experienced
Trong suốt nửa sau của thế kỷ 19, phương Tây chứng kiến
a dramatic intensification of international connectivity due to four
liên kết quốc tế gia tăng rất mạnh nhờ vào
advancing technologies--
4 công nghệ tiên tiến. Đó là
trains, steamships, the telegraph, and the postal system.
hệ thống tàu hỏa, tàu thủy, thư điện tín và bưu điện.
These developments transformed people's expectations of what was
Những tiến bộ này thay đổi mong ước của con người thời đó
possible in much the same way that today electronic communications have
cũng như các phương tiện truyền thông điện từ hiện hay
shaped our own expectations of what the 21st century has to offer us.
thay đổi cuộc sống của chúng ta ở thế kỷ 21.
As early as the 1830s, the arrival of a letter from far away could inspire a
Vào đầu những năm 1830, một lá thư từ phương xa có thể khơi dậy
sense of wonder in the recipient.
sự tò mò trong người nhận.
By the 1860s, transatlantic telegraphy provoked utopian and sometimes
Vào những năm 1860, bức điện tín vượt đại dương khơi dậy niềm hạnh phúc,
hysterical expressions of joy in the expectation that instant
hân hoan với mong muốn
communications would put an end to the scourge of war.
chấm dứt chiến tranh.
The period 1880 to 1914 saw a level of global economic integration that
Giai đoạn 1880 - 1914 chứng kiến mức độ hội nhập kinh tế quốc tế
matched or even exceeded that of the global economy today.
bằng hoặc thập chí vượt xa mức độ hội nhập của nên kinh tế thế giới hiện tại.
The investment capital that flowed around the world, much of it
Vốn đầu tư chảy khắp thế giới, phần lớn đến từ
originating in London, contributed to the economic development of the former
London, đóng góp vào sự phát triển kinh tế của các nước
colonies of the global British Empire--
từng là thuộc địa của Anh như
the United States, Canada, Australia, and New Zealand.
Mỹ, Canada, Úc và New Zealand.
Small and remote British possessions around the world, such as the Cayman
Một số nơi thuộc sở hữu của Anh như Đảo Cayman,
Islands, the Bahamas, and Hong Kong, would eventually turn into so-called
Bahamas, và Hong Kong trở thành
offshore tax havens, serving a global economic elite.
thiên đường thuế phục vụ cho giới giàu có của thế giới.
Many of these subordinate microstates remain under British
Trong số các tiểu quốc này, có nhiều nơi vẫn năm dưới
control to this day.
sự kiểm soát của Anh cho đến tận bây giờ.
Other European colonial empires established their own international
Những đế quốc châu Âu khác cũng thành lập
trade routes with their colonies in Africa, whose liberations would not
con đường giao thương với các nước thuộc địa tại châu Phi, những nước này chỉ giành được độc lập
come until the last decades of the 20th century.
vào những thập kỷ cuối của thế kỷ 20.
In fact, the oppression and exploitation of colonized populations
Thực tế, đàn áp bóc lột người dân thuộc địa
has always been an integral part of the global system.
luôn là một phần của hệ thống toàn cầu.
Raw materials and more exotic goods flowed from the colonies across the
Những nguyên liệu thô, hàng hóa mới lạ chảy từ thuộc địa
seas to Europe.
về châu Âu.
At the turn of the 20th century, an affluent inhabitant of London had
Đến thế kỷ 20, người giàu có ở London
access to many products of foreign origin years before the fateful events
đã sử dụng nhiều sản phẩm có xuất xứ nước ngoài trong nhiều năm trước khi
of August 1914 profoundly disrupted this world of unprecedented global
sự kiện tháng 8/1914 nổ ra làm chia tách
connectivity.
thế giới.
The second half of the 19th century also saw an extraordinary
Nửa sau của thế kỷ 19 cũng chứng kiến
proliferation of transnational organizations, many of which aimed at
sự tăng lên nhanh chóng của các tổ chức xuyên quốc gia, trong đó có nhiều tổ chức
improving the world in one way or another by promulgating humanitarian
hướng đến thay đổi thế giới bằng cách phổ biến tử tưởng nhân đạo
ideals or a belief in the value of knowledge to human affairs.
hoặc niềm tin về vai trò của kiến thức đối với các vấn đề của con người.
We may call these organizations and their global campaigns or movements
Ta có thể gọi những tổ chức này và chiến dịch toàn cầu của họ là
the idealistic internationalisms.
idealistic internationalism.
The Swiss businessman and social activist Henri Dunant founded the Red
Henri Dunant, doanh nhân đồng thời là nhà hoạt động xã hội người Thụy Sĩ đã thành lập
Cross in 1863.
Hội chữ thập đỏ vào năm 1863.
The Salvation Army, a Christian international charitable organization,
Salvation Army, một tổ chức tình nguyện quốc tế của người Thiên chúa giáo
was established in 1865.
được thành lập vào năm 1865.
And the world's only surviving language movement of this era,
Ngôn ngữ duy nhất của giai đoạn này đó là
Esperanto, appeared in 1887.
Esperanto, xuất hiện vào năm 1887.
Surrounded by Poland's language barriers and ethnic conflicts, Ludwig
Do rào cản ngôn ngữ của Hà Lan và các cuộc chiến dân tộc thiểu số, Ludwig Zamenhof
Zamenhof invented the artificial language known as Esperanto in the
đã sáng tạo ra ngôn ngữ Esperanto với hi vọng
hope of making peace among the warring factions.
lập lại hòa bình giữa bên giao chiến.
The French nobleman Pierre de Coubertin, an admirer of the British
Pierre de Coubetin, một quý tộc người Pháp ngưỡng mộ hệ thống thể thao của Anh,
sport system, founded the International Olympic Committee in
đã thành lập Hội đồng Olympic Quốc tế
1894 with the goal of establishing better international relations among
vào năm 1894 nhằm xây dựng mối quan hệ
the competing nations.
giữa các quốc gia tranh đấu.
The Swedish industrialist Alfred Nobel began awarding the Nobel Prizes in
Afred Nobel, nhà tư bản công nghiệp người Thụy Điển, bắt đầu trao giải Nobel
1901 to scientists from any country.
cho các nhà khoa học trên thế giới vào năm 1901.
The professed internationalist and openly racist Lord Baden-Powell
Lord Baden-Bowel, một professed internationalist và người phân biệt chủng tộc
established the Scouting Movement in 1908.
đã thành lập Hướng đạo sinh vào năm 1908.
It is worth noting that all of these second phase international
Đáng chú ý, tất cả những tổ chức ơ giai đoạn thứ 2 này
organizations, with the partial exception of Esperanto, have enjoyed
ngoại trừ ngôn ngữ Esperanto, đều đạt được
enormously successful global careers over the past century or more.
thành công lớn trong hơn thế kỷ qua.
They were and they remain today exemplars of second phase
Họ đã và vẫn là biểu tượng của
globalization.
toàn cầu hóa giai đoạn thứ 2.
Having demonstrated their usefulness, or at least their widespread appeal to
Chứng minh được vai trò hay ít nhất sức thu hút lớn đối với
the global community, these global organizations testify to the enduring
cộng đồng thế giới, những tổ chức quốc tế này là minh chứng cho
stature of venerable movements that have always claimed to represent the
các phong trào tầm cỡ đại diện cho
highest aspirations of mankind.
khát vọng cao nhất của loài người.
Perhaps some of these humanitarian activists realized at the time that
Có lẽ trong số các nhà hoạt động nhân đạo này, một vài người đã nhận ra rằng
without the practical internationalism of the Universal Postal Union,
nếu không có Universal Postal Union
established in 1874, as well as the services of the transatlantic
được thành lập vào năm 1874, cũng như các dịch vụ từ
steamship companies, their idealistic projects would have
các công ty tàu thủy xuyên đại dương thì những dự án lý tưởng của họ
faced insuperable obstacles.
sẽ gặp không ít trở ngại.